Guide to the Clifford Whittingham Beers Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Clifford Whittingham Beers papers
1878-1966
1878-1958
MS 612
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
Consists of typescript, holograph and mimeograph drafts and notes for A Mind That Found Itself by Clifford W. Beers, Yale graduate, author, founder of the Mental Hygiene Movement, and reformer in the field of mental health. Also included are printed materials, pamphlets, and clippings relating to Beers and his work in addition to photographs of Beers and his wife, the former Clara Louise Jepson.
Beers, Clifford Whittingham, 1876-1943
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Clara Louise Jepson Beers.
Scope and Contents
The Clifford W. Beers papers consist primarily of eleven different drafts of his manuscript for A Mind that Found Itself. Included in this are typed copies of dictation, holograph manuscripts in pencil, drafts with numerous annotations, elisions, corrections, additions, and readers' copies with their comments and criticisms. The manuscripts were received already numbered and in some order; no attempt has been made at more detailed collation. However, the order may be somewhat arbitrary and further research may reveal some corrections to be made in this connection.
The rest of the papers consist of printed materials, pamphlets, clippings, and articles by or about Clifford W. Beers. There are also some photographs of him and his wife. Biographical information may be found in Box 7, folder 47, "Obituaries."
Biographical / Historical
In 1908 founded the Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene; in 1909 founded National Committee for Mental Hygiene; in 1928 founded American Foundation for Mental Hygiene; founded in 1930 International Committee for Mental Hygiene; founded in 1931 International Foundation for Mental Hygiene.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Medicine; Mental health; Beers, Clara Louise Jepson, 1874-1966; Beers, Clifford Whittingham, 1876-1943 ( Mind that found itself); National Committee for Mental Health
- Inventory
  - A Mind that Found Itself
    - Ms. no. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
    - Ms. no. 2 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 4)
    - Ms. no. 3 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Ms. no. 3 (cont.) (Box 2, Folder 7 - 10)
    - Ms. no. 4 (Box 2, Folder 11 - 12)
    - Ms. no. 5 (Box 3, Folder 13 - 15)
    - Ms. no. 6 (Box 3, Folder 16 - 18)
    - Ms. no. 6 (cont.) (Box 4, Folder 19 - 21)
    - Ms. no. 7 (Box 4, Folder 22 - 24)
    - Ms. no. 7 (cont.) (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Ms. no. 8 (Box 5, Folder 26 - 28)
    - Ms. no. 9 (Box 5, Folder 29 - 30)
    - Ms. no. 9 (cont.) (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Ms. no. 10 (Box 6, Folder 32 - 34)
    - Ms. no. 11 (Box 6, Folder 35 - 37)
    - Cover for 1st edition, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Reviews, 1923-1941 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - ALS to A. P. Stokes, 1907 December 6 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - TL to George Beers, 1923
  - Printed material and clippings re: Clifford Beers, 1908-1966 (Box 7, Folder 41 - 42)
  - Pamphlets by and about Clifford Beers, 1917-1949 (Box 7, Folder 43 - 44)
  - Beers, Clifford: TMS, "Brief Account of the Origin and Growth of My Interest in Drawing and Painting," with "My Kind of Art," with printed material signed, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Printed material, articles, pamphlets re: Mental Hygiene Movement, 1919-1941 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Obituaries, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Beers, Clara Louise (Jepson), miscellaneous printed material, 1958-1966 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Clifford Beers' copy of A Mind that Found Itself, 1908 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Photographs of Clifford and Clara Beers and others, 1894-1936 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Papers of Benjamin Jepson, 1833-1913?, father of Clara Louise Jepson
    - Ms notes, "Homesteading in Kansas 1856-1858" (photostatic copies), undated (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Ms notes, "Civil War Notes 1861-1864", undated (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - ALS to Hattie Metzger, 1878 (Box 8, Folder 51)